Guide to the New York Irish History Roundtable Records AIA.018
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Irish History Roundtable Records
1867-2015
1987-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Irish History Roundtable
AIA.018
28.28 Linear Feet in 53 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 2 cassette boxes, 2 card boxes, 1 flat box, 1 media box, and 2 record cartons
28 audiocassettes
8 VHS
461 Megabytes in 77 computer files
The New York Irish History Roundtable, founded in 1984, encourages research on the history of the Irish in New York, New York, and provides a forum for professional and amateur historians and genealogists sharing an interest in this topic. The Roundtable sponsors lectures, walking tours, graduate and undergraduate scholarships and awards, exhibitions, genealogy workshops, and publishes books, a bi-annual newsletter, and an annual journal, New York Irish History. The collection documents all activities of the Roundtable from 1984 to 2011 and includes files of former officers and publications, both of the organization and on topics of interest to the officers and members. The collection consists of mainly paper material, with some digital and audiovisual material. Material in the collection includes correspondence, paper and digital drafts and published versions of Roundtable publications, photographs of events, agendas and minutes documenting meetings of the Board of Directors and Roundtable committees, and audiovisual material documenting special projects of the Roundtable.
Historical Note
Since 1984 the New York Irish History Roundtable has encouraged research and provided a forum for historians and genealogists sharing an interest in the history of the Irish in New York, New York. Past projects conducted by the Roundtable include an attempt to create an index for the newspaper Irish Echo, an oral history of people who lived in Irish neighborhoods in New York City, and the restoration of the gravestone of Matilda Tone. Past events and museum exhibits include a dinner commemorating the Irish famine in the 19th century and its effects on New York City, an exhibit on traditional Irish music and dance in New York City, walking tours of New York City cemeteries, and genealogy workshops. The Roundtable and its members contributed to the publication of a bibliography of theses and dissertations titled The Irish Experience in New York City compiled by Ann M. Shea and Marion Casey, and an anthology titled The New York Irish edited by Ronald H. Bayor and Timothy J. Meagher, both on the history of the Irish in New York City. In addition to these publications, the Roundtable publishes an annual journal, New York Irish History, and their bi-annual newsletter.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In 2004, the New York Irish History Roundtable sent a gift of 10 cubic feet. Additional donations were received in 2009 and 2018. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1997.049, 2012.083, 2012.088, and 2018.110.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Scope and Contents
The New York Irish History Roundtable Records document the activities of the Roundtable from 1984 to 2011 and include files of former officers. The collection consists of mainly paper material, with some digital and audiovisual material, and dates from 1867 to 2011, with the bulk of the material dating between 1987 and 2003. Material in the collection includes correspondence between officers and members, Roundtable publications, membership files, financial documents, photographs and programs of events, agendas and minutes documenting meetings of the Board of Directors and Roundtable committees, books on historical topics of interest to Roundtable officers, and audiovisual material documenting Roundtable projects. The collection documents the Roundtable's publications, including its bi-annual newsletter and annual journal, New York Irish History. Other publications in the collection include an anthology, The New York Irish, edited by Ronald H. Bayor and Timothy J. Meagher, and a bibliography of theses and dissertations, The Irish Experience in New York City, compiled by Ann M. Shea and Marion Casey. Material related to the Roundtable's publications includes drafts and final versions in paper and digital formats, correspondence regarding these publications, and audio recordings of presentations of chapters from The New York Irish at the 1992 meeting of the Organization of American Historians. Roundtable events and projects documented in the collection include the 10th anniversary of the Roundtable, the restoration of the gravestone of Matilda Tone in 1994 in Green-Wood Cemetery in Brooklyn, and an oral history project conducted by Roundtable members. There is a large amount of material on the exhibit, Gaelic Gotham, held at the Museum of the City of New York in 1996. This material consists of paper and born-digital material and includes correspondence regarding the planning of the exhibit by the Roundtable and the Museum, clippings and correspondence regarding the final exhibit, the public's reaction to it, and the Roundtable's 1997 report on the exhibit titled Gaelic Gotham Report. There is duplication throughout the collection, with each series documenting the same events and topics.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series. Material in each series is physically arranged in the order in which it was received from the donor. The container list for each series is arranged in alphabetical order by organization name, title of work, topic, or format.
Series I. Ann M. Shea Files
Series II. Marion Casey Files
Series III. Clare Curtin Files
Series IV. Angela Carter Files
Appraisal
Four floppy disks were deaccessioned after forensic imaging and analysis determined items contained no usable data.
One floppy disk was discarded due to mold growth, however before being removed, this disk was forensically imaged and analyzed.
Duplicates of the Roundtable's publications, off-air recordings of radio shows, and publications not related to the Roundtable or Irish history were deaccessioned.
Legal materials related to Marion Casey's dispute with the Museum of the City of New York with regards to Gaelic Gotham were removed from the collection since these items are protected by attorney-client privilege.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu or 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- History.; History -- Societies, etc. -- New York (State); New York (N.Y.) -- History; Casey, Marion R., 1962-; Shea, Ann M., 1933-; Curtin, Clare; Carter, Angela
- Series I. Ann M. Shea Files, 1867-2011; 1987-2011; 9.9 Linear Feet in 16 manuscript boxes, 2 card boxes, and 2 record cartons; 461.5 Megabytes in 39 computer files
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the files of Ann M. "Nancy" Shea and documents her work as Vice-President for Local History and Treasurer. The series spans 1867 to 2011, with the bulk of the material dating between 1987 and 2011, and includes correspondence regarding membership renewals and surveys, membership databases, Roundtable events and projects, and financial documents. The financial documents include bank statements, checks, expense statements, receipts, invoices, tax documents, and ledgers. This series also includes Shea's library of paper and digital versions of Roundtable publications, genealogy books, and books on the Irish in New York City. Special events and projects documented in this series include a project to create an index of the newspaper the Irish Echo and the compilation of the Gaelic Gotham Report.
  - Administrative files, 1988-2003 (Box 5, Folder 2, Box 8, Folder 19, Box 10, Folder 11, Box 12, Folder 20-21, Box 13, Folder 1, Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Annual meeting files, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 13, Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - Awards and scholarship files, 1996-2010 (Box 3, Folder 10, Folder 12, Box 6, Folder 9, Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Books, 1867-2008 (Box 47, Box 48)
  - Clippings, 1987-2009 (Box 4, Folder 2, Box 7, Folder 16, Box 10, Folder 7, Box 14, Folder 5, Box Shared Tamiment 014, Folder 6)
  - Contracts, 1995-1997 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence -- General, 1995-2010 (Box 3, Folder 19-20, Box 4, Folder 1, Folder 3-6, Folder 10, Box 8, Folder 14, Box 9, Folder 6, Folder 12-13, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Folder 9-10, Folder 18, Box 13, Folder 2-3, Box 14, Folder 13, Folder 16-17, Box 15, Folder 12-14)
  - Correspondence -- Grant applications, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Election files, 1994-2008 (Box 10, Folder 12, Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Events -- Genealogy workshops, 1996-2006 (Box 12, Folder 11-17, Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Events -- General, 1995-2010 (Box 3, Folder 13, Box 8, Folder 10, Folder 20-24, Box 11, Folder 5, Folder 8, Folder 16, Folder 19, Box 12, Folder 1-8)
  - Events -- New York and the Irish Famine, 1994-1995 (Box 14, Folder 10-12)
  - Financial documents, 1989-2007 (Box 5, Folder 12, Box 11, Box 13, Folder 12-15, Box 14, Folder 3, Box 15, Folder 5-10, Folder 16-17, Box 16, Folder 1-7)
  - Gaelic Gotham Report, 1995-1997
    - Paper Materials (Box 1, Folder 1-14, Box 2, Folder 1-15, Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_18_ER_5
  - The Irish Experience in New York City files, 1994-2009 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Meeting agendas and minutes, 1991-2011 (Box 5, Folder 3-7, Box 3, Folder 1, Folder 16, Box 7, Folder 10, Box 11, Folder 13, Folder 15, Box 13, Folder 10-11, Box 14, Box 15, Folder 3, Folder 11)
  - Membership Files, 1991-2001
    - Paper Materials (Box 3, Folder 7-9, Folder 11, Folder 14, Folder 17-18, Box 4, Folder 11-12, Box 5, Folder 1, Folder 13, Box 6, Folder 1-7, Folder 10-12, Box 7, Folder 1-9, Box 8, Folder 15-18, Box 9, Folder 1-2, Folder 3-4, Box 13, Folder 6-9, Box 14, Folder 2, Box 15, Folder 4, Folder 15, Box 16, Folder 8-11)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_18_ER_1
  - The New York Irish, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - New York Irish History, 1994-2007
    - Paper Materials (Box 3, Folder 3-4, Folder 15, Box 5, Folder 8-10, Box 6, Folder 8, Box 9, Box 11, Folder 11, Box 13, Folder 5, Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_18_ER_2
  - New York Irish History Roundtable blog, 2008 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - New York Irish History Roundtable Newsletter, 1988-2011 (Box 3, Folder 2, Box 7, Folder 11, Box 9, Folder 3, Box 11, Folder 9, Folder 17-18)
  - New York Irish History Roundtable website, 1996-2006 (Box 5, Folder 11, Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Officer files, 1995-2001 (Box 7, Folder 13-15, Box 10, Folder 2-3, Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Press contacts, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Projects -- Commemoration of the United Irish Rebellion of 1798, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 8-9, Box Shared Tamiment 014, Folder 8)
  - Projects -- Emigrant Savings Bank, 1996-2003 (Box 10, Folder 13-14, Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - Projects -- Irish Echo indexing, 1989-1997 (Box 3, Folder 5-6, Box 45, Box 46)
  - Projects -- Oral history, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Projects -- Small projects files, 1995-2005 (Box 7, Folder 18, Box 8, Folder 1-7, Box 9, Folder 11, Box 12, Folder 19, Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Publications Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series II. Marion Casey Files, 1984-2015; 18.51 Linear Feet in 33 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, 1 card box, 1 cassette box, 1 CD box, 1 flat box, and 1 media box; 28 audiocassettes; 8 VHS; 9.98 Megabytes in 20 documents and 7 floppy disks
  This series contains the files of Marion Casey and documents her work as President of the Roundtable and as a member of the Board of Directors, as well as her continued membership in the Roundtable. The series also documents Casey's time working as a curator for the Museum of the City of New York and her involvement creating Gaelic Gotham: A History of the Irish in New York. The series dates between 1984 and 2015. Material in this series includes correspondence, drafts and published versions of Roundtable publications, photographs and other material documenting Roundtable events, and paper and audiovisual material on Roundtable projects. Projects documented in this series include the compilation of The Irish Experience in New York City by Casey and Ann M. Shea, an oral history project undertaken by the Roundtable, the 10th Anniversary of the Roundtable, and the restoration of Matilda Tone's gravestone in Green-Wood Cemetery. The oral history project is documented in paper correspondence, notes, and secondary sources on conducting oral histories, as well as audio and video recordings of oral history interviews of people who lived in Irish neighborhoods in New York City. This series also contains correspondence, notes, and audio and video recordings of events at the Keeping the Tradition Alive: A History of Irish Music and Dance in New York City exhibit at the Museum of the City of New York in 1991. Correspondence, grant proposals, VHS tapes, audiocassette tapes, floppy disks, exhibit scripts, object lists, budgets, newspaper clippings, and promotional materials related to the Museum of the City of New York's exhibit Gaelic Gotham: A History of the Irish in New York, are also housed within this collection.
  Casey's role in the publication of The New York Irish is documented in this series through drafts and proofs of articles included in the book, paper and born-digital notes, minutes and notes from meetings about the project, correspondence, and event ephemera. The correspondence includes plans for events celebrating the publication of the book, as well as correspondence with contributors to and the publishers of the book. Also included are audio recordings of presentations by contributors to the book from the Organization of American Historians conference in 1992. Files labeled "Mixed documents" include correspondence, notes, clippings, agenda and minutes on various topics including Roundtable publications, events, and research interest of Roundtable officers and members. Publications files include correspondence, drafts, published versions of New York Irish History, the Roundtable's newsletter, promotional ephemera, and correspondence regarding printing and graphic design. Membership files include correspondence with and about members and dues, renewal forms, and surveys conducted of members.
  - Administrative files, 1987-1993 (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
  - Clippings and press releases, 1987-1994 (Box 22, Folder 7, Box 24, Folder 2, Box 29, Folder 6-11)
  - Correspondence -- Funding sources, 1987-1991 (Box 21, Folder 11-12, Box 22, Folder 1-2, Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- General, 1985-2015 (Box 20, Folder 6-10, Box 30, Folder 1-3, Box 31, Folder 12, Box 32, Folder 1, Folder 4, Folder 14, Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence -- Legal, 1988-1991 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Election files, 1997-1998 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Events -- Genealogy workshops, 1988-1992 (Box 21, Folder 13-14, Box 32, Folder 15)
  - Events -- New York and the Irish Famine, 1994-1995 (Box 25, Folder 12-14, Box 26, Folder 1-7)
  - Financial documents, 1984-1993 (Box 21, Folder 1-10)
  - Gaelic Gotham and other Museum of the City of New York exhibition materials, 1990-1997
    - Paper Materials (Box 50, Box 51, Box 52, Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Box 57, Box 58, Box 59, Box 60)
    - Audio Materials (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Audiocassette 018.0022-018.0030)
    - Video Materials (Box 61, Vhs 018.0031-018.0035)
    - Graphic Materials (Box Shared Tamiment 081, Folder 22)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_18_ER_6
  - Internet Committee, 1996-1998 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - The Irish Experience in New York City, 1990-1996 (Box 24, Folder 4-6, Box 37, Folder 1-14, Box 38, Folder 1-5)
  - Keeping the Tradition Alive: A History of Irish Music and Dance in New York City, 1990-1991 (Box 22, Folder 4-6, Folder 9-12, Box 44, Cassette 018.0012-018.0015, Box 49, Cassette 018.0019-018.0020)
  - Meeting minutes, 1984-2000 (Box 28, Folder 10-13, Box 29, Folder 1-2, Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Membership files, 1984-2003 (Box 23, Folder 1-4, Folder 7, Box 25, Folder 5, Box 28, Folder 4-6, Box 31, Folder 5-8, Folder 13, Box 32, Folder 18, Box 46)
  - Mixed documents, 1987-2003 (Box 25, Folder 6, Folder 9, Box 31, Folder 10, Box 32, Folder 13, Folder 16-17, Folder 19-20)
  - The New York Irish, 1989-1997
    - Paper Materials (Box 25, Folder 10, Box 33, Folder 1-12, Box 34, Folder 1-11, Box 35, Box 36, Box 38, Folder 6-14, Box 39, Box 40, Folder 1-14, Box 41, Folder 1-9, Box 46)
    - Audio Materials (Box 44, Audiocassette 018.0016-018.0018)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_18_ER_4
  - New York Irish History, 1988-2004 (Box 22, Folder 8, Box 25, Folder 11, Box 27, Folder 1-19, Box 28, Folder 1-3, Box 29, Folder 5, Box 31, Folder 9, Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 17)
  - New York Irish History Roundtable Newsletter, 1987-2000 (Box 20, Folder 11-12, Box 23, Folder 8-10, Box 32, Folder 8-11)
  - New York Irish History Roundtable website, 1996-1999 (Box 31, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, 1988-1996 (Box 28, Folder 7-9, Box 30, Folder 4-25, Box 31, Folder 1-4)
  - Projects -- Commemoration of the United Irish Rebellion of 1798, 1995-1997 (Box 26, Folder 8-11, Box Shared Tamiment 014, Folder 9)
  - Projects -- Irish Echo indexing, 1988-1993 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Projects -- Oral history, 1986-1991 (Box 24, Folder 7-9, Box 25, Folder 1-3, Box 44, Cassette 018.0001-018.0011, Box 49, Cassette 018.0021)
  - Publications, 1985-2000 (Box 23, Folder 11-16, Box 24, Folder 1, Box 29, Folder 3-4, Box 31, Folder 11, Box 32, Folder 5-7)
  - Scholarship files, 1990-1993 (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Series III. Clare Curtin Files, 1989-2007; 2.2 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes
  This series contains the files of Clare Curtin and documents her work as Secretary of the Roundtable. The series dates between 1989 and 2007 and includes membership materials, correspondence between officers, and drafts and published versions of Roundtable newsletters and New York Irish History. The membership material consists of renewal forms, lists, and surveys conducted in 1991 and 1995.
  - Clippings, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 20, Folder 2-3)
  - Election files, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Mailing lists, 1994-1997 (Box 18, Folder 2, Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1994-1997 (Box 18, Folder 1, Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Membership files, 1991-1997 (Box 17, Folder 4-16, Box 18, Folder 4-9, Box 19, Folder 1-6)
  - New York Irish History, 1989-1991 (Box 16, Folder 13, Box 17)
  - New York Irish History Roundtable Newsletter, 1999-2007 (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
- Series IV. Angela Carter Files, 1986-2000; 1.3 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes; 106 kilobytes in 3 computer files
  This series contains the files of Angela Carter and documents her work as Corresponding Secretary, Newsletter Editor, and Recording Secretary. The series dates from 1986 to 2000 and documents Carter's work on The New York Irish and the Gaelic Gotham Report. Materials include correspondence and clippings on both publications, paper drafts of The New York Irish, paper and born-digital drafts of the Gaelic Gotham Report, and statements for the bank account connected to The New York Irish.
  - Gaelic Gotham Report, 1992-1999
    - Paper Materials (Box 41, Folder 9-10, Box 42, Folder 1-13)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_18_ER_3
  - The New York Irish, 1986-2000 (Box 41, Folder 8, Box 42, Folder 14, Box 43, Folder 1-11, Box Shared Tamiment 014, Folder 7)